Hans Gadow Papers 1907-1914 Mss.B.G11
American Philosophical Society
Hans Gadow Papers
1907-1914
Mss.B.G11
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet
A prolific and diverse scholar, Hans Friedrich Gadow (1855-1928), wrote on such topics as birds, Mexican peoples and animals, reptiles, and other vertebrates. Born in Germany in 1855, Gadow studied anatomy with Ernst Haeckel in Germany before moving to England, where his research on avian anatomy and systematics had broad influence. He was Curator of the Stricklandian Collections at Cambridge University and a Reader on the morphology of vertebrates. The Gadow Papers consists of twenty letters (1907-1914) from Hans Gadow to William Morris Colles and to Colles' firm 'Author's Syndicate' that discuss Gadow's work "Through Southern Mexico" (1908). Colles was an agent who helped writers to publish their work. The early letters deal with editorial changes to the book, the later letters are about A & C Black, a publishing firm, which Gadow believed had not properly compensated him for his contributions to "The Lost Link," a book he co-authored with Ernst Haeckel. Most of the letters are very brief and do not discuss personal matters in Gadow's life nor do they contain much information on Gadow's scholarly work, except for references to the editorial process. Similarly, they provide no information on Gadow's travels to Mexico.
Gadow, Hans, 1855-1928
Related Archival Materials note
Little survives of Gadow's correspondence. The major collections are:
Henry Bradshaw Papers, Hans Gadow letter to HB Reference BRA /2/43 Covering dates 24 Aug. 1885, Cambridge University.
Gadow, Hans Friedrich (1855-1928) notebook held at The University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada.
Gadow, Hans Friedrich c.100 items corresp. Natural History Museum, London, United Kingdom.
Bibliography
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Acquired 1979 (accession no. 1979-1638ms).
Scope and Contents note
The Gadow Papers consists of twenty letters (1907-1914) from Hans Gadow to William Morris Colles and to Colles' firm 'Author's Syndicate' that discuss Gadow's work "Through Southern Mexico" (1908). Colles was an agent who helped writers to publish their work. The early letters deal with editorial changes to the book, the later letters are about A & C Black, a publishing firm, which Gadow believed had not properly compensated him for his contributions to "The Lost Link," a book he co-authored with Ernst Haeckel. Gadow wanted Colles to assist him in retrieving funds that he believed that the publishers owed him for the book. He also wrote to ask for information on the status of sales for his book "Through Southern Mexico". Most of the letters are very brief. The letters do not discuss personal matters in Gadow's life nor do they contain much information on Gadow's scholarly work, except for references to the editing process. Similarly, they provide no information on Gadow's travels in Mexico.
Biographical/Historical note
A prolific and diverse scholar, Hans Friedrich Gadow (1855-1928), wrote on such topics as birds, Mexican peoples and animals, reptiles, and other vertebrates. Born in Germany in 1855, he studied anatomy with Ernst Haeckel in Germany before moving to England, where his research on avian anatomy and systematics had broad influence. In 1892, Gadow published his classification system of birds, partially founded on the work by Maximilian Furbinger. Alexander Wetmore used Gadow's classification of birds for his own work, published in 1930 and James L. Peters adapted Wetmore's research, in turn, for his "Checklist of Birds of the World" series.
Gadow was Curator of the Stricklandian Collections at Cambridge University and a Reader on the morphology of vertebrates. He and Haeckel co-authored the book "The Lost Link," published in 1898 and Gadow collaborated with Richard Sharpe on the "Catalogue of Birds in the British Museum", he wrote two volumes on the Passeriformes (perching birds). Gadow wrote two volumes in the British Museum series: Catalogue of the Passeriformes, or perching birds, in the collection of the British Museum. Cichlomorphae: pt.V. containing the families Paridae and Laniidae (titmice and shrikes) and Certhiomorphae (creepers and nuthatches), no. 8, and Catalogue of the Passeriformes... Cinnyrimorphae: containing the families Nectarinidae and Meliphagidae (sunbirds and honey eaters), no. 9. Gadow also authored a volume in "The Cambridge Natural History," series on reptiles and amphibia.
In 1908, Gadow published "Through Southern Mexico," which described the ruins, natural history, flora, and people of the area between Oaxaca and Vera Cruz and included many illustrations (primarily photographs). Gadow also wrote a book on Jorullo in Mexico. Jorullo is a cinder-cone volcano that erupted continuously between 1759 and 1774. Gadow's book on Jorullo was a study of the effect that the volcanic eruption had on the wildlife and fauna of the region and was published posthumously in 1930.
Author's Syndicate; Colles, William Morris; Haeckel, Ernst Heinrich Philip August; Gadow, Hans, 1855-1928. Through Southern Mexico; Mexico--Description and travel
- Hans Gadow Papers, 1907-1914; 0.25 lin. feet (Box 1)
  - To William Morris Colles, 1907 Sept. 18; ALS, 1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Scope and Contents note
    Mentions suggestions by Mr. Withersby that he had made for the editing of Gadow's book. Recommends a personal meeting with Colles to discuss the issues.
  - To: William Morris Colles, 1907 Oct 18; ALS, 1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Publication of his book, completion of the editing process, discusses drawings and pictures of natural history objects.
  - To William Morris Colles, 1907 Nov. 7; ALS, 1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Requests that the issue of publication of his book be settled and writes that he has sent his manuscript to Mr. Withersby, but he is unsatisfied with the reply that he received from a clerk.
  - To William Morris Colles, 1908 Feb. 14; ALS,1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Gadow wants a bigger allowance but is hesitant to cause any problems, also discusses photographs that were ruined and the replacement of these with illustrations
  - To William Morris Colles, 1908 Feb. 18; ALS, 1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Gadow is reluctant to comply with certain editorial changes to his manuscript that he does not agree with. Discusses grammar changes that Gadow will implement in his manuscript. Also gives an example of how Gadow believes that changes should be made.
  - To William Morris Colles, 1908 Feb. 28; ALS, 1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Gadow reports that he has sent his manuscript to a Dr. Spear for his opinion on the book and that Gadow believes that most of the manuscript should be completely finished..
  - To William Morris Colles, 1909 May 20; ALS, 1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Gadow requests that Colles send him an agreement written in the spring of 1908 between Gadow and Mr. Withersby.
  - To Author's Syndicate, 1909 June 16; ALS, 1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Gadow requests that the Author's Syndicate send to him the accounts related to his book "Through Southern Mexico".
  - To William Morris Colles, 1909 June 18; ALS, 1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Gadow confirms that he received a check from Colles and discusses some financial matters in relation to the publication of his book. Writes that he has heard that the price of his book in the United States is too high and this will result in poor sales. reports that he has had letters in response to his book from Sweden and France among other countries.
  - To William Morris Colles, 1909 July 9; ALS, 1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Gadow requests Colles' assistance with A. & C. Black over "The Last Link," by Ernst Haeckel and partially written by Gadow, and published in 1898 and 1899. Gadow has not received money from the sales of the book and he has also been charged money for its advertising.
  - To William Morris Colles, 1909 July 16; ALS, 1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Gadow presents to Colles more details on the situation with Black publishers. Believes that he should have received a set amount of money after enough books had been sold. Contends that he has not received appropriate compensation.
  - To Author's Syndicate, 1909 July 27; ALS, 1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Reports on a disagreement between Black's publishers and Gadow on how to include books that had been sold in America and Britain's colonies. Black's had contended that they should not be included in the sales figures
  - To William Morris Colles, 1909 August 5; ALS, 1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Deals with the issue of the Black family publishers and what Gadow believes is owed to him by the publishing firm. Bases his claim on how many books had been sold and the interest that should be given to him.
  - To Author's Syndicate, 1911 Jan. 19; AL, 1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Brief letter inquiring into why Gadow has not received a half-annual statement on his book "Through Southern Mexico".
  - To Author's Syndicate, 1911 July 28; ALS, 1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Gadow requests that the Author's Syndicate discover if Black's has continued to publish and sell "The Last Link."
  - To Author's Syndicate, 1911 Sept. 16; ALS, 1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Gadow writes about his book, "Through Southern Mexico."
  - To Author's Syndicate, 1912 June 8; ALS, 1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Gadow agrees to give his share of his book, "Through Southern Mexico," to Mr. Withersby for twenty pounds.
  - To Author's Syndicate, 1913 Feb. 7; ALS, 1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Gadow requests that he be sent a list of how many copies of "Through Southern Mexico" have been sold.
  - To Author's Syndicate, 1913 Dec. 15; ALS, 1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Gadow comments on giving Mr. Withersby the royalties of his book "Through Southern Mexico."
  - To Author's Syndicate, 1914 June 25; AL, 1p.; Gadow, Hans
    Gadow wants a statement about "Through Southern Mexico" to be sent to him, because they had failed to do so earlier.